<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Israels just jvdge; or, The maiestrats brest-plate, against the darts of pride, envy, &amp; hipocrisie: being enemies to iustice, mercy, &amp; humility. Presented to the jmpartial maiestrats of this nation, especialy in the western parts, from whence the author (by Gods providence) drew his first breath; wishing them health here, and all happiness hereafter. / Written by Charles Hammond.</title>
            <author>Hammond, Charles, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E899_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865849</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865849</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118100</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118100)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 135:E899[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Israels just jvdge; or, The maiestrats brest-plate, against the darts of pride, envy, &amp; hipocrisie: being enemies to iustice, mercy, &amp; humility. Presented to the jmpartial maiestrats of this nation, especialy in the western parts, from whence the author (by Gods providence) drew his first breath; wishing them health here, and all happiness hereafter. / Written by Charles Hammond.</title>
                  <author>Hammond, Charles, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Crowch, in Hosier-lane, for the author.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With title page woodcut representing a figure of Justice.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "January [the] 7th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Justice, Administration of --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118100:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>JSRAELS</hi> Juſt <hi>JVDGE;</hi> OR, THE Maieſtrats Breſt-plate, AGAINST THE Darts of Pride, Envy, &amp; Hipocriſie: being enemies to Iuſtice, Mercy, &amp; Humility. Preſented to the Impartial Maieſtrats of this Nation, Eſpecialy in the Weſtern parts, from whence the Author (by Gods providence) drew his firſt breath; wiſhing them health here, and all happineſs hereafter.</p>
            <p>Written by CHARLES HAMMOND.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Bring you men of wiſedom and of underſtanding, and known amongſt your tribes, and I will make them rulers over you: and I charged your Judges that ſame time, ſaying: heare the controverſies between your Brethren, and Judge Righteouſly between every Man and his Brother, and the ſtranger that is with him, ye ſhall have no reſpect of Perſons in Judgement but ſhal heare the ſmall as well as the great: ye ſhall not feare the face of Man for the Iudgement is Gods.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.16, 17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blindfolded figure of justice with scales and sword</figDesc>
               <p>Iuſtice.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>London; Printed by: <hi>E. Crowch,</hi> in <hi>Hoſier-lane,</hi> for the Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="allowance">
            <pb facs="tcp:118100:2"/>
            <p>Seene and allowed of, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered according to Order.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>MY Book being paſt the Preſſe, may freely goe,</l>
               <l>To ſerve his Countrey, I would have it ſo;</l>
               <l>Truth being his leader, what Foe needes he feare,</l>
               <l>His cauſe being good, beſides his Conſcience cleare:</l>
               <l>Jle take thy part, if any thee appoſe?</l>
               <l>To Juſtice, and to Truth, they muſt be Foes.</l>
               <l>I will not blaze thy Armes, but this Jle ſay,</l>
               <l>Truths Banner on thy Creſt thou doſt diſplay:</l>
               <l>A Freind to none, but thoſe that be,</l>
               <l>Lovers, of Juſtice, Mercy, and Humility.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118100:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his much Reſpected Friends in</hi> Somerſet-ſhiere; <hi>eſpecially in the towne of</hi> Taunton. the <hi>Author</hi> wiſheth all Truth, Peace, and Unity, to floriſh amongſt you.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Know not into whoſe hands this my ſmal Booke may light into, but I have ſo much a cofindence in Truth, that heel never ſhame his Maſter, nor for my part I will never be aſhamed to own him, if there be any thing diſliking to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of any Man in my Booke, let him not unload his ſtomack openly to the Author, for that will but ſhew he hath a foule inſide, though he carries a fair outſide, this is but a Cordiall gathered from Truths Garden, the Scripture of ſuch hearbs that is reliſhing to all that loveth the Garden or the Gardener, the Phyſitian of Souls will tell you ſo, nor doe I give it you out of malice to doe you harm, but hoping it may work with you for the good of you and yours in this life, and that to come: if you take it any otherwiſe; the Garters Motto Jle preſent you with, <hi>evil to them that evil thinks:</hi> I wiſh
<pb facs="tcp:118100:3"/>you better then you wiſh your ſelves, that is that you would know your ſelves what you have been, what you may be, and what you muſt be, The firſt you know, the ſecond God knows, the laſt all Men knows you muſt be brought to Judgment, when we all ſhall heare but two Sentences: come or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. And whatſoever you owe me (being the Author of this little Booke) if it be ill will, I will returne you by bill of Exchange, this wiſh from the botom of my heart, that you may both deſerve and have the firſt ſentence of come you Bleſſed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it through Chriſts merits, and receive it from his mouth, which ſhall be the Prayer of him which deſires Mercy and Truth to meet together, and Righteouſneſs and Peace to kiſs each other.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Hammond.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118100:3"/>
            <head>ISRAELS Iuſt JUDGE; OR The <hi>Maieſtrats</hi> Breſt-Plate, <hi>AGAINST</hi> The Darts of <hi>Pride, Envie,</hi> and <hi>Hipocriſie;</hi> being Enemies to <hi>Juſtice, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Humility.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <p>He hath ſhewed the O man what is good; and what doth the <hi>Lord</hi> require of thee but to doe juſtly, and to love mercy, and to wallk; humbly with thy God.</p>
               <bibl>Micah. 6.8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ajeſtracy, and Mineſtry, are the two main Pillars that upholds a Nation, ordained of God himſelfe ever ſince the <hi>Iſralites</hi> bondage in <hi>Egypt,</hi> to juſtifie the truth of it, if you pleaſe to begin from <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron,</hi> which were the firſt that God gave the Law to, and end with the Revelation, you ſhall find God own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and maintaing it in the Law. Chriſt and his Apoſtles both admoniſhing others, and ſubmitting to it themſelves in the Goſpell; the taking away of thoſe Pillars from any Nation or People, you ſhall find it was a fore-runner of Gods judgements, as you may read in ſeverall places, but eſpecially in the booke of Judges; Idolatry, Adultery, Opreſſion, Murther, diſdaining one another, was the common ſins of the Children of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> for then did every Man doe what ſeemed good in his owne eyes. But the ſubject of my diſcourſe is bent upon another cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and with my beſt endeavours and Gods permiſſion to up hold thoſe Pillars, ſo far forth as they be not like gilded Sepul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118100:4"/>make a fair ſhew when there is nothing but rottenneſſe within, ſuch upholders either of Citty, Burrough, or Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any other place that hath not a wall of hearts to defend them; which is the Majeſtrats Fort-Royall; the judgements of God will ſoone lay their honor in the duſt, if he find once they have gone beyond their Commiſſion: if he ſummons not them here with his Court Marſhall which is death, let them looke for disgrace and infamy to ceaſe on them, and pull them from their Chaire of Juſtice, and leave them to the cenſure of envy and malice.</p>
            <p>Well let us ſee then what is required of Majeſtrates, alas, an eaſie charge that God gives them, his commiſſion may very well be kept, he requires of them to doe juſtice, love mercy, and walke humbly before him; and will they not perform it? yes: they'l tell you they doe well, their own eyes ſhall be witneſſes, and their own conſciences the Juries, and in this booke ſhall they be found guilty or not guilty, of breaking his Commiſſion, when they ſhall appeare before the Judge of all the Earth, who ſhall render every Man according to his works. Well the firſt the Lord requires is to doe juſtice. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 17, 18. the Lord ſhewes the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> what juſtice he requires? <hi>The Lord your God is God of Gods and Lord of Lords, great mightie and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which accepteth no Perſons, nor taketh reward, who doth right to the Fatherleſs and Widdow, and loveth the Stranger, giving him food and raiment, love you therefore the Stranger, for ye were ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>againe</hi> Exod. 23. <hi>Thou ſhalt not recieve a falſe tale, neither ſhalt thou put thy hand with the wicked to be a falſe witneſs; thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to doe evill, neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in a controverſy to decline after many to overthrow the truth. Thou ſhalt not eſteeme a poore Man in his cauſe, nor thou ſhalt not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the right of the Poore in his Suit, thou ſhalt keepe thee far from a falſe matter, thou ſhalt take no gift, for the gift blindeth the wiſe, and perverteth the words of the Righteous, thou ſhalt not oppreſs at ſtranger.</hi> Man may wonder why the Lord doth take ſo much care, and gives ſuch great charge in his Law to <hi>Moſes</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Poore, and ſtrangers: we muſt needs conjecture that when he delivered the Law to <hi>Moſes,</hi> it ſhould ſtand for a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118100:4"/>to all ages, for at that time there was no poore, for they were all going towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> and till they came there they all far'd alike, they had <hi>Manna</hi> to eat, and the Wilderneſſe for their poſſeſſion for 40 years together, and when they came to <hi>Canaan</hi> it was a Land that flowed with Milke and Honey: Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lord know their hearts; great Men would be puft up ſo with Pride, Ambition, and Envy, that the Poore ſhall goe to wrack in after Ages: as you ſhall find in the Prophets times. I wonder where we ſhall heare or read in any ages, the Poore and Strangers ſo little rewarded, and leſs regarded then in our times, the poore cries, the rich ſays let them worke, will not they worke, (cryes the Majeſtrate) let them be whipt; which ſome perhaps are not able to worke, or if they can, their worke is not able to maintain their charge; they not giving themſelves and ſtopping the charity of thoſe that would gives? Reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelves you great ones of the Earth; you that fare deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly every day and thinke not of the afliction of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> you that lays out all on your backs and bellies, or hoards up all in your coffers and cheſts, and knows not who ſhall injoy it: But why ſhall I, or how dare I tell you of theſe things? yes, I muſt; if I ſhould not ſpeake, I thinke ere long the ſtones would ſpeake to ſome of you: I ſpeake no more but what I have the word of God for my warrant, <hi>He that giveth to the Poore lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the Lord,</hi> ſaith our Saviour: Chriſt owneth the poore, and ſtrangers too, you will find it ſo at the day of Judgement; the 25 of <hi>Mathew</hi> will ſhew it you? ſtrangers cries ſome of you, why they are vagrants; they hinder us of our Trading, cryes the Shop-keeper, doth he come further then he can goe home at night, our Majeſtrates and we will hold together, right or wrong let him not ſpeake for himſelfe, no nor ſuffer no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſpeake for him, our wils ſhall be our Law; and though we can find neither the Law of God, nor the Laws of the Land to juſtifie our actions, our lips are our owne, and who is Lord over us. Pſalm, 12.4 <hi>Now for the oppreſſion of the needy, and the ſighs of the Poore:</hi> I <hi>will up ſaith the Lord and will ſet at liberty whom the wicked hath ſnared.</hi> verſe 5. Solomon <hi>ſaith when the Righteous are in authority the People rejoyce, but when the wicked
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118100:5"/>beare rule the People ſigh,</hi> Peov. 29.2, <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no injury to a ſtranger, nor oppreſs him, ye ſhall not trouble the Widdow nor Fatherleſs child, if thou vex or trouble ſuch, and ſo he call and cry unto me, I will ſurely heare his cry: then ſhall my wrath be kindled, and I will kill you with the Sword, and your Wives ſhall be Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and your Children Fatherleſs:</hi> Exod. 22. v. 21, 22, 23, 24. The Lord is juſt in all his Judgements, he tels Man, doe as thou wouldſt be done by, the ſame meaſure you meat, ſhall be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured to you or yours againe. <hi>Rob not the Poore becauſe he is poore, neither oppreſs the aflicted in Iudgment, for the Lord will defend their cauſe, and ſpoil the ſoul of them that ſpoil them.</hi> Prov. 22, 22. <hi>Open thy mouth for the dumb, in the cauſe of all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of deſtruction, open thy mouth, judge Righteouſly, and judge the aflicted and the Poore. Prov.</hi> 30.8. The Lord would have Men in authority ſpeak for thoſe that either dare not or cannot ſpeak for themſelves: many a good cauſe is overthrown of the poor mans, for want of Men of power and knowledge to ſpeake for them: it hath been an old Proverb, might overcomes right? either his purſe or his place overcomes the poore man: how dare you goe to Law with a Majeſtrate cryes ſome, one Majeſtrate will take anothers part; if they doe, let them have a care it be in a juſt cauſe, if not; the poore mans cauſe will be pleaded before that Judge that hath no reſpect of perſons, he will pannell your owne conſciences for a Jury to condemn you, if you doe not juſtice? heare you Judges and Majeſtrates, <hi>God ſtandeth in the aſſembly of Gods, he judgeeh amongſt Gods: how long will you judg unjuſtly, and accept the Perſons of the wicked, doe right to the poore and fatherleſs, doe juſtice to the poore and needy, deliver the poore and needy, ſave them from the hand of the wicked, I have ſaid you are Gods, and you are all Children of the moſt high, but ye ſhall dye as Men, and ye Princes ſhall fall as others. Pſal.</hi> 82. This may ſtrike a terror both to Majeſtrate and People; doth God tearm them Gods? it will confute thoſe that would cry downe that authority whom God gives ſuch a Title to on Earth. <hi>Let every man be ſubiect to the higher powers, for their is no power but of Gods, and the powers that be, are ordained of God; giue to all Men therefore their dues, tribute to whom you owe tribute, cuſtom to whom you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118100:5"/>owe cuſtome, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe are to whom you owe feare, honor te whom you owe honor:</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>O you Jndges and Majeſtrates are you Gods? then let the Law of God be your guide: he that turneth away his eare from hearing the Law, even his Prayer ſhall be abominable.</hi> Pro. 28 9. <hi>Heare ye O Kings, and learn you that are Iudges of the ends of the Earth, for the rule is given you of the Lord, and power from the moſt high which wi I try your works and ſearch out your imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe you being Officers of his Kingdom have not judged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, nor kept the Law, nor walked after the will of God, horibly and ſuddainly will he appeare unto you, for a hard judgment ſhall they have that beare rule: for he that is low is worthy of mercy, but the mighty ſhall be mightily tormented, for he that is Lord over all ſhall ſpare no Perſon, neither ſhall he feare any greatneſſe, for he hath made the ſmall and the great and careth for all alike, but for the mighty abideth the ſorer triall.</hi> you may read it in the 6 chap. of the <hi>Wiſedom of Solomon,</hi> though it be in the <hi>Apocraphy,</hi> yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes it good in the GoſPell, <hi>Acts,</hi> 10. v. 3, 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Epbe.</hi> 6.9, <hi>Col.</hi> 3, 25. What Men oſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtrats to be then, in whoſe hand God gives the Sword of Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, who ſhould repreſent that inviſible God in the viſible ſeat of juſtice, we find in the 18 of <hi>Exod. Iethro</hi> the Prieſt of <hi>Midi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Moſes</hi> Father in law admoniſheth his Son what Men he ſhould chuſe; provide thou Men among all the People, Men of courage, fearing God, Men dealing truly, hating covetouſneſſe. O! that is a ſin I am afraid too much uſed both by Majeſtrats and others to in this Narion; now in theſe times covetouſneſs is the root of all evill, and tis no marvell ſo much wickedneſſe ſprings up in moſt plaecs, where ſuch great roots of covetouſneſs is planted: <hi>Moſes</hi> though chiefe ruler of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the counſell of his Father-in-law <hi>Iethero,</hi> he did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe him for his age, age is honorable, if they be not gray before they are good: age is a crowne of Glory, where it is found in the way of Righteouſneſs. Prov. 16. <hi>Happy is that gray head that is crownd with Righteouſneſs, but unhappy is that gray head that is environed with envy and covetouſneſs.</hi> Juſtice is the Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſs of all vertues, and the trueſt tryall of a good Man; but the covetous heart is a very mint of fraud, it can readily coyn falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118100:6"/>upon all occaſions. Covetouſneſs is the mother of all ſins whatſoever: There is no evil that a covetous man will not put in practice, ſo goods may come of it: You cannot name that ſin but he will ſwallow it in the ſweet broth of commodi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y. He that is greedy of gain, will ſel the truth, ſel his friend, his father, his maſter, his conſcience; nay more, with <hi>Ahab,</hi> ſel himſelf for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. When once men are bewitcht with the love of money, as <hi>Iudas</hi> was, a ſmall matter would make them ſel Chriſt himſelfe, were he now on the earth to be ſold. All vices rule where geld reigns. He that is inſlaved to that ſin, may be wrought by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than to any thing. Covetouſneſs is the grave of all goodneſs; it eatt out the very heart of grace, by eating graces out of the heart. When Avarice gets poſſeſsion, it turns grace onto doors: No ſuch impedim nt to converſion and ſalvation as it isf <hi>Miniſters</hi> may wel wonder their Sermons take no better; but. <hi>God</hi> tels us the reaſon, Ezek. 33. <hi>They ſis before thee, and hear thy word, but their hearts go after covetouſneſs.</hi> It deſtroyes more ſouls than all other ſins put together, as the Apoſtle intimates, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6, 10. You shall ſooner hear of a hundred malefactors contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the gallows, than of one covetous miſers in his bed. Our Saviour expreſly affirmeth, <hi>that is eaſier for a Camel to goe through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man</hi> (that is, a covetous Rich man) <hi>to enter into the kingdome of heaven,</hi> Luke 18.25. And the Apoſtle that, <hi>no covetous man can look for any inheritance in the kingdome of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd of God,</hi> Epheſ 5:5, 1 Cor. 6, 9, Well may it be accounted good counſel of <hi>Iethro</hi> to cauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> to chuſe thoſe men for Officers that hated that ſin of Covetouſneſs: for how can he doe Iuſtice to others, that is ſo unjuſt to himſelfe? Or what cares he what affliction he layes upon his neighbours body when he hath ſo little mercy on his own ſoul? There are few Rich men that will not rather offend the divine majeſty than the temporal authority: nor doe they goe to Chuych to ſerve God but the ſtate, which they uſe not to ſave their ſoules, but charges. There is no Religion in them but the love of money, <hi>A</hi> covetous man goeth more to the aſſemblies for fear of the Law than love of the Goſpel, and more out of cuſtome than conſcience, as <hi>Cain</hi> offered his ſacrifice, and ſo will God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118100:6"/>accept of it. He ſits down at table, but hath no ſtomack to eat his ears are at Church, but his heart is at home; and as his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, ſuch is his praying: He may afford God his voice, but his heart is rooted and riveted to the earth. <hi>They have not cried to me,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>with their hearts when they howled upon their beds; it was but for corn and wine,</hi> Hoſea 7.14. O that God had the ſame place in mens affections that riches, honour, and pleaſure hath. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they are not high minded and that they truſt not in uncertain riches, but in the living God, which giveth us abundantly all things to enjoy.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.17. And well doth that man deſerve to periſh, that ſo loves the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as that he leaves the Creator. If a covetous man ſhould hear me, all's one with him, an ounce of Gold with him will weigh down whatſoever can be alledged from the Word: He can like <hi>Canan</hi> well enough, ſo he may enjoy his fleſh-pots of <hi>Egypt</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; and can love the bleſſing, with <hi>Eſau,</hi> but he will not loſe the potage: And in caſe he cannot gain by being Religious, his care ſhall be not to loſe by it, and that Religion ſhall ſerve him beſt that is beſt cheap, and will coſt him leaſt. Any doctrine is welcome to him but that that beats upon good works: Nor wil he ſtick with the Sages to fall down and worſhiy Chriſt, but he cannot abide to preſent him with his gold. The love of money, and coming in of gain, is dearer and ſweeter to the muckworm than the ſaving of his ſoul. The Scribes and Phariſees, who were covetous men, ſhut their eyes ſtopt their ears againſt all our Saviour did, and ſaid; yea they ſcoft at his preaching, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.14. Of all ſorts of ſinners that Chriſt preached unto, he was never ſcorned and mockt but by them when he preached againſt Covetouſneſſe, and what is the reaſon but this; Rich worldlings think the nſelves ſo much the wiſer as they are the richer, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may all pray that <hi>Iethro's</hi> counſel which he gave to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> may be conſidered by thoſe that ſit at the helm of Iuſtice to ſteer this nation in this troubleſome ſea of theſe times, that they would provide men of courage, fearing God, men dealing truly, hating covetouſneſſe. See what <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> did when he brought the people to the Lord God of their fathers, <hi>and he ſet Iudges in the land, in all the ſtrong cities of Iudah citie by citie, and be ſa<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to the Iudges, take heed what ye do, for you execute not the judgment of man
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118100:7"/>but of the Lord, and he will be with you in the cauſe &amp; judgement wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore now let the feare of the Lord be upon you, take heed and doe it, for there is no iniquity with the Lord our God, neither reſpect of Perſons, receiving of reward,</hi> 2 Cron. 19.5, 6, 7. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee O Man what is good, and what the Lord doth require of thee but to doe juſtly, to love mercy, and to walke humbly with thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Muſt Mercy be joyned with juſtice, yes, Government founded on Juſtice, and Mercy, doth knit and unite the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth in love and vnity, which is the true upholder of Peace and Plenty: whereas injuſtice and cruelty brings war, ruine and miſery; injuſtice and cruell oppreſſion was <hi>Iſraels</hi> deſtruction; ſhall any think that are guilty of the ſame to goe unpun ſhed? no; <hi>Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> Gods mercy is above all his works, for it is of the Lords Mercy we are not conſumed, nay;, it is Gods mercy we doe not conſume one another, for we ſeeke the ruine and deſtruction of one another; may it not be ſaid to <hi>England</hi> as it was ſaid to <hi>Jſrael,</hi> heare ye the word of the Lord ye Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (or <hi>England you may ſay</hi>) for the Lord hath a controverſy with the inhabitants of the Land, becauſe there is no Truth, nor Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, nor knowledge of God in the Land, by ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and committing Adultery; they break out, and blood toubeth blood; I referr it to any rationable Chriſtian if this Propheſie be not fulfil'd in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtay, the ſubject of my pen cals ſo much for Iuſtice, that ſhall forget Mercy: and my deſire is to have them goe hand in hand together, and always doe in thoſe Towns where Pride and Covetouſneſs ſteps not in to part them; but you may aske what this Mercy is that God requires of Man; of Mercy there is <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo ſorts, there is mercy to the Poore, and mercy to thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, or ſtranger; and all ends in Charity. <hi>I was a hungrey and ye <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave me meat, thirſty and ye gave me drinke, I was a ſtranger and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e lodged me, <hi>I</hi> was naked and ye clothed me, <hi>I</hi> was ſick and ye viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed me, <hi>I</hi> was in Priſon and ye came unto me.</hi> Mat. 25.35, 36, 37.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118100:7"/>
            <p> But what may we ſay now, what will many in theſe times doe to fulfill Chriſts word in doing this to the Poore for his ſake; for the hungry I have r courſe Proverb, but it is finely obſerved by too many, you may break your neck before you breake your faſt at their houſes: or you thirſty, they will make you bleed more then you ſhall drink; or you a ſtranger, theyl lodge you but it ſhall be in the <hi>Cage</hi> or <hi>Bridewell,</hi> and there you ſhall pay for it too; or you naked; theyl cloth you, but it ſhall be with ſtripes? or you ſick, they'l viſit you if you have any thing to give them, or theyl cry God helpe you, and ſo leave you (ſmall helpe or comfort from them) or you in Priſon, they'l come t'ye or ſend t'ye, but it ſhall be to intrap you, to keepe you there the longer, for there you ſhall ſtay till you haue ſatisfied their malice, or paid the uttermoſt farthing: nay; though you owe them nothing, yet if they owe you ill will: in Priſon you ſhall ſtay till they have paid you what they owe you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Baile or main-prize, and if they be great ones if you tell them there is Law for them, as well as for others they'l bind you over to that they perhaps want themſelvs; for threatning of them.</p>
            <p>Tis true as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The tender mercies of the wicked are cruell.</hi> How can that Man looke for any mercie from God, that is ſo mercileſſe to his Brother? doe not disdaine me for telling thee thy faults whoſoevers you be, for taking the poore and ſtrangers parts; or you rich, you have but an uncertain leaſe of it, it is neither for years nor life, neither for you nor your heirs, no longer then your Lord pleaſes, when you have exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all your Bowels with the ſpider to contrive a ſlender webb of an uncertain inheritance here on Earth, one puffe of wind blown from the Almightie, carries all awaie? for riches taketh her ſelfe to her wings and flieth awaie, <hi>Prov,</hi> 23, 45, <hi>All rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are uncertain, but thoſe that are ill gotten are moſt uncertain;</hi> as examples of all ages witneſſeth; <hi>Perſis</hi> Son and heire was faine to learn the Black-ſmiths trade to relieve his neceſſiitie. And <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth that victorious Emperor after he had fought fiftie two pitch Battels, became a petitioner for a prepentary to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118100:8"/>maintain him in his old age, and <hi>Geliner</hi> that potent King of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> was brought ſo low, that he intreated his friend to ſend him a Harpe, a ſponge, and a Loafe of bread; a Harpe to conſort with his miſery, a ſpunge to drie up his tears, and a loafe of bread to ſatisfie his hunger there is inumerable ways to become poore, Fire, a Thiefe, a falce Servant, Suirtyſhip, Truſting, of bad Cuſtomers, and many the like hath brought many rich men to poverty, and this is the only wind that blows up the bladder of theſe times: Riches are like Snow-bals ſcrapt up together til the Sun ſhineth, and God breatheth upon it; and then it conſumes to nothing: heare this O ye that ſwallow up the needy, even to make the poore of the Land to fail; tell me now why you will not doe as you would be done by; are you rich? you may be poore, have you Houſes to live in, your Fathers were ſtrangers in the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> your Children may be ſtrangers in the Land of their nativity, for ought you know, the Lord takes care for the poore, Chriſt takes care for the poore, and will you profeſſe your ſelves followers of Chriſt, and will you grow careleſs of them, and inſtead of feeding them, eat up the poore, as the Lord ſaith; tis no wonder the Lord takes ſo much care for them in the Scriptures: and ſo little for the rich, for they will take care for themſelves; he knows ſo long as he lets them alone, <hi>Soul take thy eaſe, there is treaſure laid up for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a day, But O foole this night thy ſoule ſhall be taken from thee, and whoſe ſhall alt that be then? thou hadſt better ſay as</hi> David <hi>did, keepe me O Lord from thoſe that hath their portions in this life.</hi> Then conclude with me, be you mercifull as your heaverly Father is mercefull, <hi>Luke. 36. Bleſſed are the mercifull for they ſhall obtain mercy,</hi> it was never known that God ſuffered a bountifull and mercyfull Man to want, if the cruelty of times or other affictions brought him low, he wanted not a contenied mind to beare it out. <hi>He that giveth to the Poore ſhall never lack.</hi> Prov. 28, 27. A rare priviledg never to want, yet a bargaine of Gods own making; Plenty ſhall furniſh the Table where Charity takes away and gives to the Poore. <hi>He that hath pitey on the Poore lendeth unto the Lord and that which he hath given will he repay him againe.</hi> Prov. 16.17. The Lord is content to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118100:8"/>acknowledge himſelf the charitable mans debter, our gracious Redeemer doth acknowledge himſelf gratified and ingaged, as himſelf doth acknowledge, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. The poor mans hand is Chriſts treaſury; ſo a man becomes a creditour to his Saviour <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and he will pay him a hundred to one in this world, and a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hereafter. Heaven and earth ſhall be empty before he ſhall be empty before he shall want a royal payment. Charity is an act of Chriſtian policy; for we shall receive our own with great intereſt, as it fared with the widdow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> whoſe hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of meal, and cruſe of oyl that she relieved the Prophet with, the more she ſpent, the more she had, ſo shall that precious oyl beſtowed on the poor for Gods ſake be returned upon our heads in great meaſure, which makes Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſay, the charitable man is the greateſt uſurer in the world: This will be ſtrange thinks ſome, that to give away our goods is the way to increaſe them; it is, if faith be joyned with your works. But admit God ſhould not anſwer thy greedy deſire in multiplying thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, he'll do that which is better, give thee a competency with a more contented mind; therefore truſt God with <hi>Abraham,</hi> who <hi>above hope believed under hope.</hi> Rom. 4 18. For faith is to God as <hi>Bathsheba</hi> was to <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſo in favour, that the King will deny her nothing that good is. Thus you ſee, if the old teſt or new teſt be true, not getting, but giving is the ready way to abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. And if you will not believe Gods word, no man ought to beleive you.</p>
            <p>So much for Juſtice and Mercy, Humility comes after, as willing to wait upon Iuſtice and Mercy, as we would deſire truth joyned with peace and plenty. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good, and what the Lord doth require of thee, to do juſtly, love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fear of the Lord is the inſtruction of wiſdome, and before ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour goeth humility.</hi> Prov. 15.53. The more God advanceth thee to honour, the more thou oughteſt to humble thy ſelf: Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and humility are the onely means to enrich us with Gods bleſſings, but pride and unthankfulneſſe is the onely way to make God withdraw from us, and take away from us both himſelfe and his choiceſt bleſſings too. <hi>Aeſops</hi> Crow not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118100:9"/>content with her own likeneſs, borrowed a feather of every bird, and ſhe became ſo proud that ſhe ſcorn'd them all, which the birds obſerving, came and pluckt each one their feather back, and ſo left her naked? even ſo God deals with all proud ungrateful Perſons: I thinke I may ſay in theſe times wherein Pride doth ſo abound, if every bird had his owne feathers, they would be left as bare as Aeſops crow, and then like owls they may walke about by night, for by day they would be diſpiſed by all that ſees them: but I deſire the Peacocks of theſe times to looke downe to their feet, for they muſt needs be very foule when they are treading the paths of deſtruction, <hi>Pride goeth before deſtruction, and a haughty mind before a fall; better it is to be of an humble Spirit with the lowly, then to divide the ſpoil with the proud.</hi> Prov. 16, 18, 19 When <hi>Sanl</hi> was little in his owne eyes, God made him head o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the twelve Tribes of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> and gave him abundance, but when out of his greatneſs, he abuſed his place and gifts, God tooke them all away; but moſt remarkeable is the example of <hi>Nebucadnezzar</hi> who aſcribing all to himſelfe; ſaid, is not this great <hi>Babell</hi> which I have built by the might of my power and the Glory of my Majeſty? was preſently deprived of his Kingdom and all that he had, and ſent to graze with the Beaſts: and ſo likewiſe of <hi>Herod</hi> when he ſate on the Judgement ſeat and made an orration in royall Apparrell, the People cryd the voice of God and not of Man; and he never rebukt them, but tooke that honor upon him, but imediately the Augell ſmote him becauſe he gave not Glory to God, ſo that he was eaten with worms? he muſt know and all that ſit on judgment ſeats, though God cals them Gods they muſt not be deified by Man like the true God: I have ſaid ye are Gods but ye ſhall dye like Men? they are no more in Gods eyes then thoſe that ſtands before them for juſtice, nor ſhall have no more favour ſhewed them at the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall feat at the laſt day? take heed you that ſit at the bench of Juſtice, if Humility leads you not up, at laſt Pride will throw you downe: what man is he that out of the height of pride or envy will tearme true honeſt poor Men the ſcums of the World: <hi>He that mocketh the poor reprocheth him that made him, and be that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth at deſtruction ſhall not be unpuniſhed.</hi> Prov. 17.5, Before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118100:9"/>the heart of a Man is haughty, and before Glory goeth Holineſs: <hi>Prov.</hi> 18, 12. if there be a hollow in a vally lower then another, thither the water gathers, and the more lowly we are in our owne eyes, the more lowly we are in Gods; <hi>Unto him will I looke ſaith the Lord, even to him that is of a nutrit Spirit, and that trembleth at my words.</hi> Eſay. 57 15. There can nothing make us more accptable to God, then the conſcience of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe, when with <hi>Iacob</hi> we can ſay. O <hi>Lord I am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the leaſt of all thy ways which thou haſt ſhewed unto thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, for with my ſtaffe I paſſed over</hi> Jordan. <hi>and now I am become thy bonds man.</hi> Man ſhould conſider from whence he came, and whether he muſt, what he is, and what he muſt be: there is as much reſpect of ſouls before God, as there is difference in ſouls in the grave, no; it is the heart that God requires, and it muſt be a humble heart, to <hi>Samuell</hi> when he was ſent to <hi>Ieſſe</hi> by the appointment of God to anoint a King amongſt his ſons: <hi>Samuel</hi> lookt on <hi>Liab</hi> being a Man; it ſeemed in his eyes fit for a Crown, by his Perſon, his deportment and outward behaviour. <hi>But the Lord ſaid to</hi> Samuel, <hi>looke not on his countenance, nor on the height of his ſtature, becauſe I have refuſed him.</hi> 1 Samuel, 16. For God ſeeth not as Man ſeeth, for Man looketh one the outward appearance, but the Lord beholdeth the heart, when all his Sons was cal'd that were there, ſaith <hi>Samuel:</hi> is there no more Children but theſe? and <hi>Jeſſe</hi> ſaid; there is vet a little one that keepeth ſheepe, and <hi>David</hi> was ſent for, <hi>And the Lord ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and anoint him for this is he.</hi> There is a great deale of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Gods chuſing and Mans chuſing: Man looks upon the outward bravery, God looks upon the inward humility, it is not means but manners that makes a Gentleman; ſome will take acception if they be not writ Eſquires or Gentlemen, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny buſineſs that comes to them: indeed there be many by their place may write Eſquires, but being turnd out perhaps not find a coat of Armes to write Gentleman. Afterwards Collonell <hi>Morgan</hi> in the low Countreys having occaſion to ſend to the <hi>Prince of Orenge</hi> a letter, ſent it by an Enſigne of his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, delivering his Letter and meſſage, the Prince aſked him how long he had been a Souldier under Collonell <hi>Morgan?</hi> he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118100:10"/>anſwered he was no Souldier, he was an Enſigne: the Prince returnd a Letter to the Collonell, he thought he had been ſo much a Souldier that he would not make Officers that were no Souldiers and wiſhed him to take from him his colours and give him a pike, and let him firſt learne to be a Souldier, and then he is the fitter to be an Officer, he that hath firſt been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, knows the better how to command, a Man that is proud in his office, is like a foole in a Morice-dance, more lookt upon, &amp; laught at, then reſpected or regarded. Gentility if it be not flampt in the heart by Humility, it can never be knockt into their head by force or polecy, for example; meet you with a true borne Gentleman, his hat in his hand as ſoone as yours? he'l be as ready to give age the way, as he ſhall give him: be he poore or rich, and ſo they bring up their Children: take a new upſtart Gentleman which may give for a motto in his ſcutchin, of Armes theſe verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Means</hi> I <hi>have got: though breeding</hi> I <hi>lack,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You may blaze my Armes by the coat on my back:</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>This man, Sir, if you meet him either a horsback, or foot, you quickly know him, if on horsback, pride whips on his horſe a gallop, and bids him keep his way, though your horſe be ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to goe out, as if he'll over you, or elſe pride throws his maſter headlong in the dirt, as many times it falls out to fulfil the Proverb, <hi>Pride will have a fall.</hi> Meet him in the ſtreet, if you fear his great looks, and worship his fools painted coat, he'll look a ſquint upon you, and ruſſels up his coat or cloake like a Peacocks tayl, and think you have done but your due to worship this golden Calf. But if you take no notice of him, he will take no notice of you, and pick a hole in your coat for not idolizing his rich coat. But give me leave to ſtay my pen, and not beſtow ink and paper on times painted babies, which if they were to be ſold for their virtues, would not yeeld eight ſhillings a groſs; for ſome of them have not the wit to act a part in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet-play, but what muſt come from anothers mouth: But my ſubject is Juſtice, Mercy, and Humility, which affords matter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to treat on for the paper: I intend to write on Mercy, and Humility cannot be hid in honour or gentility. As their hearts
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118100:10"/>by humility opens their eyes of mercy upon the poor, the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the needy; they ſeeing your good works may glorifie your father which is in heaven; and their prayers, hearts, and hands ſhall be a wall of defence for you in the time of trouble. Pray give me leave, as I began let me make an end, which was with Iuſtice, which is all I deſire for man; and Mercy from God, him have I offended both in thought, word, and deed, from him, and through the merits of my Saviour I look for mercy. My con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tels me I have broke the laws of God, and ſo we muſt all cry guilty: Mercy nor favour looke I not from man, but truth; equity, and juſtice, which I hope that juſt God ſhall ſo guide their hearts that heare my cauſe, that without reſpect of perſons I shall have Iuſtice shewn me. Iuſtice in ancient times was pictured blind, repreſenting the unpartialneſs of her heart: She'll hear all, but ſees none; her eyes shall not corrupt her heart with the habit or love either of plaintif or defendant, but in her left hand, which is next her heart, she holds the ballance of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice weighing rightly the cruſe; then gives ſhe judgement by her two Judges, Truth and Equity, then hath ſhe her ſword ready drawn in her right hand to execute Judgement upon the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſo makes ſhe the Law of God perfect with this motto.</p>
            <q>
               <l>I <hi>heare and ſee not, yet</hi> I <hi>underſtand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And judge aright the cauſe</hi> I <hi>take in hand.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>So Ile conclude with the words that the Lord ſpake to the Children of <hi>Jſrael</hi> by Zack. 7.9. <hi>In the time of their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity execute true judgemet, and ſhew mercy and compaſſion every Man to his Brother, and oppreſs not the Widdow and the Fatherleſs, the ſtranger nor the poore, and let none of you imagine evill againſt his Brother in his heart,</hi> for this is all the Lord doth require of thee O man; to do juſtly, love mercy: and walke humbly with thy God: and this thou muſt performe: be thou high or low, rich or poore, judge or jury, it is a ſhort leſſon to read, a heard leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to learn, and a eaſy leſſon to be forgot, thou muſt have God for thy ſchoolmaſter, judge or Lawgiver, thou muſt have Chriſt for thy merciful tutor, and by thy humility thou ſhalt have the holy ſpirit that proceeds from both, repeating this leſſon always to thee <hi>Every man do ſeeke the face of the Ruler, but every mans judgment com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the Lord.</hi> Prov. 29.26,</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
